Guide to the Center for Canadian Studies records, 1971-1993
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Center for Canadian Studies records 1971-1993
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Center for Canadian Studies.
0.5 Linear Feet 500 Items
The Center for Canadian Studies was established as an independent center devoted to the study of Canada in 1973.
The collection includes reports, newsletters, clippings, announcements, conference programs, occasional papers, memoranda, brochures, slides, curricula, and other materials. Materials range in date from 1971-1993.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Center for Canadian Studies records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974, 1976, and 2002.
Historical Note
In 1970, Richard A. Preston (W.K. Boyd Professor of History at Duke and former Professor of History at Royal Military College of Canada in Kingston, Ontario) was invited to offer a one-semester undergraduate course in Duke University's Distinguished Professor Seminar series. As a consequence of student interest in the material, a new semester course on the history of Canada was introduced into the regular curriculum. The Commonwealth Studies Center (founded in 1955) already focused on Canada, and through its fellowship program, it brought one Canadian graduate student to the Duke campus each year.
In the fall of 1973, the Center for Canadian Studies was established after being awarded grants from the Office of Education and the William H. Donner Foundation. Conceived as an autonomous unit of Duke's International Studies Center, it worked closely with the Commonwealth Studies Center but remained administratively separate. The Center's name officially changed to the Center for North American Studies in January 1997. July 2003 saw the Center's name change once again and the Center for North American Studies became the Center for Canadian Studies.
Collection Overview
The collection includes reports, newsletters, clippings, announcements, conference programs, occasional papers, memoranda, brochures, slides, curricula, and other materials relating to the Center. Materials range in date from 1971-1993.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject files.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Canada -- Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina -- Durham
Duke University. Center for Canadian Studies
Preston, Richard A., 1910-
Duke University -- Curricula
Related Material
Richard A. Preston papers, circa 1745-1987 (bulk 1956-1987)
Duke University Archives
Commonwealth Studies Center records, 1954-1982
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Association for Canadian Studies in the United States, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1973, 1983-1984
  - Canada. International Development Research Center, 1974
  - Clippings, 1973-1991
  - Curricula Prepared for Elementary and Secondary Schools, 1978-1979
  - Newsletter, 1977-1986
  - Chronological File, 1973-1993
  - Papers, 1979, 1985-1986
  - Reports, 1973-1978
  - [Slide show, circa 1980]